IEGOR RIEPIN

Personal Information Background: ==

Email: iegor.riepin@tu-berlin.de

LinkedIn: iegor-riepin/

Personal page: https://iriepin.com/

I am a research scientist with expertise in energy economics, energy policy, operations research, and related programmable matter. I am particularly interested in mathematical models, their applications to real world problems, their limitations, and the role in decision making.



It is these interests that bring me to my current role as a postdoc researcher at the Energy Systems group @ TU Berlin. The overarching goal of our work is to find cost-effective opportunities for climate neutrality.

Aside from my research, I enjoy astrophotography, reading about space exploration, related discoveries and just good sci-fi books. I truly believe in the value of open science, and I try to contribute by sharing my code, data and teaching materials.

EDUCATION

PhD in energy economics (2015-2022)

University: Brandenburg Technical University C-S, Germany PhD advisors: Prof. Felix Müsgens and Prof. Luis Baringo

My cumulative thesis is titled "Modeling challenges of modern energy markets: studies on uncertainty, complexity, and constant change" and is published in open access.

Grade: Summa cum laude (1.0)

Master degree in Power Engineering (2012-2014)

University: Brandenburg Technical University C-S, Germany Honours degree based on the overall performance (1.2)

Bachelor degree in Heat Power Engineering (2008-2012)

University: ZSEA, Ukraine

Honours degree based on the overall performance (4.98/5)

WORK EXPERIENCES

2022 March→ Postdoctoral researcher | Energy system modeler @ ENSYS

We use methods from operations research and mathematical optimisation researching the most cost-effective pathways to reduce greenhouse gas emissions in energy systems. Our group also maintains the PyPSA ecosystem - an open-source python environment for state-of-the-art energy system modelling.

I lead the modelling work for the 24/7 Carbon-Free Energy by 2030 project that is a research collaboration with Google. Details are at the project page 247cfe.github.io and at GitHub github.com/PyPSA/247-cfe

Since Q2 2024, I work on the RESILIENT research project, financed by public funds. The project aims to improve our abilities to plan energy infrastructure in a resilient way.

2021 September \rightarrow **2022 February** Research fellow | Energy Systems Modelling lead @ Chair of Energy Economics at BTU C-S

I was leading a team of researchers working on modelling of energy markets, acquisition and implementation of third-party research projects with energy industry and government stakeholders. My job in leading the team included managing ongoing research activities, modelling workflow and making sure we do the right things.

2014 November \rightarrow **2021 August** Research fellow @ Chair of Energy Economics at BTU C-S

I have carried out research on energy economics and energy systems modeling. The topics included infrastructure investments, decisions under uncertainty, robust planning of energy systems, risk-aversion, sector coupling and energy auctions. In this period, my PhD supervisor and I developed an "Energy systems modelling" study course at BTU C-S. The class focuses on the intersection of energy economics, operations research and systems modelling. The course gets usually very warm feedback from students. Apart from that, I was teaching "Power System Economics 101/102" classes.

OTHER EXPERIENCES

2024 → Freelance consultant | Research scientist @ Green Deal Ukra□na

Aside my research, I support the Green Deal Ukrauna project that aims to set up a Think Tank that will provide modelling-based guidance for Ukrainian government, policymakers, and society in rebuilding the Ukrainian economy and energy sector during and after this terrible war.

ACADEMIC RESEARCH VISITS

- **2023 August** → **2023 September** I had a research visit to a Scalable Systems Laboratory headed by Prof. Victor Zavala at University of Wisconsin-Madison, USA. My work there focused on optimization problems for space-time load shifting by data centers.
- 2019 September → 2019 October I had a research stay in a Sustainable Energy Systems Integration & Transitions Group headed by Prof. McPherson at UVIC, Victoria BC, Canada. My work there focused on robust optimization algorithms applied to electricity system expansion problems. Victoria BC is simply a fantastic place.

THIRD-PARTY
FUNDED PROJECTS

- **2024 April** → @TUB RESILIENT. Funding: BMWK (CETpartnership project). Project webpage: https://resilient-project.github.io/
- **2022** March \rightarrow @TUB 24/7 Carbon-Free Energy by 2030. Funding: Google. Project webpage: https://irieo.github.io/247cfe.github.io/ Background: Google sustainability
- 2021 → 2022 @BTU TransHyDE (System analysis of transport solutions for green hydrogen). Funding: BMBF (Federal Ministry of Education and Research). Cooperation: >30 partners. Project webpage: wasserstoff-leitprojekte.de

2017 @BTU – Design of auctions for market premia for onshore wind generation: theoretical and experimental testing. Cooperation: CERGE-EI. Summary

2016 @BTU – Strategy 2020: modelling of forward prices for natural gas in European gas markets. Funding: industry partner. Cooperation: r2b energy consulting GmbH.

2014 \rightarrow 2016 @BTU – Fundamental gas market analysis in a context of the German energy transition process. Funding: gas trading utility. Cooperation: r2b energy consulting GmbH. Summary

PEER-REVIEWED
JOURNAL ARTICLES

In review: Spatio-temporal load shifting for truly clean computing

Riepin I., Brown T., Zavala V.

Working paper: https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00036

Code: https://github.com/Irieo/space-time-optimization

In review: Power System Benefits of Simultaneous Domestic Transport and Heating Flexibility in Great Britain's Energy Transition

Franken et al.

Working paper: https://zenodo.org/records/10781213

Blog post @ Centre for Net Zero

In review: On the means, costs, and system-level impacts of 24/7 carbon-free en-

ergy procurement Riepin I., Brown T.

Working paper: https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07876

Code: https://github.com/Irieo/247-procurement-paper

Environmental research letters (2024): Temporal regulation of renewable supply for electrolytic hydrogen

Zeyen E., Riepin I., Brown T. DOI: 10.1088/1748-9326/ad2239

Working paper: https://zenodo.org/records/8324521

Code: https://zenodo.org/record/7457441

Energy Economics (2023): Risk aversion and flexibility options in electricity markets

Möbius T., Riepin I., Müsgens F., van der Weijde A. H.

DOI: doi.org/10.1016/j.eneco.2023.106767

Working paper:https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.04088 Code: https://github.com/BTU-EnerEcon/RiskAv

Applied Energy (2022): Adaptive robust optimization for European strategic gas infrastructure planning

Riepin I., Schmidt M., Baringo L., Müsgens F.,

DOI: doi.org/10.1016/j.apenergy.2022.119686

Code: https://github.com/Irieo/ARO-GasInfrastructure

Working paper: www.optimization-online.org/DB_HTML/2021/10/8654.html

Energy Policy (2022): Policy choices and outcomes for the global competitive procurement of offshore wind

Jansen M., Beiter P., Riepin I., Müsgens F. Juarez Guajardo-Fajardo V., Staffell I.,

Bulder B., Kitzing L.

DOI: 10.1016/j.enpol.2022.113000

Data: https://zenodo.org/record/6524754

Working paper: https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.12548

Applied Energy (2021): Modelling uncertainty in coupled electricity and gas sys-

tems—Is it worth the effort?
Riepin I., Möbius T., Müsgens F.
DOI: 10.1016/j.apenergy.2020.116363
Code: https://github.com/Irieo/IntEG

Working paper: https://arxiv.org/abs/2008.07221

Nature Energy (2020): Offshore wind competitiveness in mature markets without subsidy

Jansen M., Staffell I., Kitzing L., Quoilin S., Wiggelinkhuizen E., Bulder B., Riepin I., Müsgens F.

DOI: https://www.nature.com/articles/s41560-020-0661-2

Code: https://zenodo.org/record/3906565

Supplementary data: https://zenodo.org/record/3906325

Nature Energy News & Views: Leaving the competition in its wake

Media coverage: 125 news stories

Energy Journal (2019): Seasonal flexibility in the European natural gas market

Riepin I., Müsgens F.

URL: http://www.iaee.org/en/publications/ejarticle.aspx?id=3779

Code: https://github.com/Irieo/SeasonalFlex

Cambridge Working Papers Series:

DOI: doi.org/10.17863/CAM.43923 | Abstract | Non-Technical Summary

CONFERENCE PAPERS

IEEE EEM (2022): Modeling of Extreme Weather Events—Towards Resilient Transmission Expansion Planning

Bernecker M., Riepin I., Müsgens F. DOI: 10.1109/EEM54602.2022.9921145

IEEE EEM (2020): Regret analysis of investment decisions under uncertainty in an integrated energy system

Möbius T., Riepin I.

DOI: 10.1109/EEM49802.2020.9221935

IEEE EEM (2018): Integrated electricity and gas market modeling—effects of gas demand uncertainty.

Riepin I., Möbius T., Müsgens F. DOI: 10.1109/EEM.2018.8469790

IEEE EEM (2018): Is offshore already competitive? Analyzing German offshore wind auctions.

Müsgens F., Riepin I.

DOI: 10.1109/EEM.2018.8469851 | Preprint | Video

IEEE EEM (2016): Modelling of world LNG market development: focus on US

investments and supplies.

Montenegro R., Riepin I., Hauser P. DOI: 10.1109/EEM.2016.7521361

ZSEA (2011): Usage of solar energy for heating service and domestic water heating. Riepin I. VII all-Ukrainian scientific conference. Vol. 2, pp. 78 - 83.

ZSEA (2011): Ukrainian market prospects in the field of alternative energy sources. Riepin I. The annual conference for graduate students. pp. 186 - 192.

OTHER PUBLICATIONS

Project study (2023): The value of space-time load-shifting flexibility for 24/7 carbon-free electricity procurement

Riepin I. and Brown T.

DOI: https://zenodo.org/records/8185850

Project study (2022): System-level impacts of 24/7 carbon-free electricity procurement in Europe

Riepin I. and Brown T.

DOI: https://zenodo.org/record/7180098

SSRN paper (2021): Grok it and use it: Teaching energy systems modeling Riepin I., Sgarciu S., Bernecker M., Möbius T., Müsgens F. DOI: https://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.4320978

Working paper (2015): A note on climate policy negotiations at the threshold of COP-21 in Paris

Müsgens F., Poudineh R., Riepin I.

A note by Oxford Institute for Energy Studies & BTU CS

Science explainers & media appearances

I am not a media person, but occasionally I happen to be in the media to talk about my research in a way that is understandable and interesting to a broader audience.

- The Week in Green Software: Modeling Carbon Aware Software Podcast @ Environment Variables (November 2023)
- On space-time load-shifting flexibility for 24/7 carbon-free electricity procurement

Panel discussion @ Linux Foundation Energy summit Paris, June 2023

- The era of 'negative-subsidy' offshore wind power has almost arrived Guest post @ CarbonBrief (2020)
- Offshore-Windenergie subventionsfrei?
 Guest post @ e|m|w.trends (2020)

Public talks and scientific outreach

An up-to-date list of my talks can likely be on https://iriepin.com/

On the role of 24/7 CFE in accelerating advanced clean electricity technologies

Slides @ Eurelectric 24/7 CFE Hub workshop, May 2024

Code: https://github.com/PyPSA/247-cfe

- Signals for spatio-temporal load shifting in 24/7 clean computing Slides @ DTU Cool Data project final workshop, February 2024 Code: https://github.com/Irieo/space-time-optimization
- On space-time load-shifting flexibility for 24/7 carbon-free electricity procurement

Slides @ Eurelectric 24/7 CFE Hub, October 2023

Code: https://github.com/PyPSA/247-cfe/tree/v0.3

- System-level impacts of 24/7 carbon-free electricity procurement in Europe Slides @ EWI Cologne research seminar, November 2022 Code: https://zenodo.org/record/7181236
- 24/7 A new paradigm for power procurement? Slides @ ENERDAY Conference, May 2023 Slides @ European Climate and Energy Modelling Platform, October 2022 Code: https://github.com/PyPSA/247-cfe/tree/v0.2
- European Natural Gas Infrastructure Expansion Planning: An Adaptive Robust Optimization Approach Slides @ EWI Cologne guest talk, July 2021 Slides @ European Conference on Operational Research, Athens, 2021 Code: https://github.com/Irieo/ARO-GasInfrastructure
- On the costs of ignoring uncertainty and the value of perfect information: a toy model. Slides | Code @ Doctoral seminar, BTU CS, 2019
- Robust optimization of electricity system expansion Slides | Code @ University of Victoria seminar, 2019
- Economic impacts of uncertainty in integrated electricity and gas markets Slides @ 30th European Conference on Operational Research, Dublin, 2019
- Integrated electricity and gas market modelling—effects of gas demand uncertainty

Slides @ EEM2018 Conference, Lodz, 2018

Slides @ PhD seminar Cottbus-Leipzig-Dresden, 2018

- Integration of electricity and gas market models Slides @ Energy modelling seminar, IER, Universität Stuttgart, 2018
- Application of non-linear and complementarity problems for natural gas market modelling Slides @ Research seminar on mathematical economics, BTU CS, 2017
- Natural Gas Storages in Competition with Alternative Flexibility Sources Slides @ 39th IAEE International Conference, Bergen, 2016 Slides @ PhD seminar Cottbus-Leipzig-Dresden, 2016
- Mathematical modelling of natural gas markets Slides @ BTU research seminar, Cottbus, 2016 Slides @ Mathematical modelling workshop, Frankfurt, 2015
- Prospects for Shale Gas Exploration in Europe: Ongoing Experience Slides @ 38th IAEE International Conference, Antalya, 2015

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2014 → Teaching and supervising graduate students on topics related to energy economics and energy systems modeling.

 $2017 \rightarrow 2020$ "Energy Systems Modeling" (course development, selected lectures, tutorials, supervision of student projects)

Lecture: Prof. Dr. Felix Müsgens

Some materials are available at github.com/Irieo/ESM

2014 → **2018** "Power System Economics 101" (Winter terms | tutorials) and "Power System Economics 102" (Summer terms | tutorials)
Prof. Dr. Felix Müsgens and Prof. Dr. Stefan Zundel

Scholarships & awards

I am grateful for the following scholarships and awards that supported me during my studies:

- Promotionsstipendium des Landes Brandenburg, GradV, Postgraduate scholarship 2017-2019
- Rheinstahl foundation study scholarship, Master degree 2014
- STIBET study scholarship, DAAD, Master degree 2013
- Zaporizhia city administration scholarship, Bachelor degree 2010

COMPUTER SKILLS

Programming, scripting and markup languages Python and data science stack (daily), Git (daily), Snakemake (daily), LATEX(daily), GAMS (many years of project-related use, research and teaching).

Languages My mother tongue is Ukrainian and Russian, but almost everything I do in private and in scientific work is in English. I also speak German when needed.

FOLLOW THE STARS

I do enjoy astrophotography and even have a small blog page about it. When I am done with science, I will be a space cowboy.

Fun fact

My wonderful wife holds a PhD in Energy Economics and is also an energy modeller & research scientist by profession. I wish one of us would have chosen to be a doctor.

Berlin, May 2024